Welcome back, everyone.
After we've been through
some more technical sessions
about Julia and Neuroblox
and how to code in both,
now we'll move more
into the neuroscience,
and we'll start with some
basic units of neuroscience,
talking about neurons, neural
mass models, and sources.
And these three
categories basically
are the outline for
this morning's lecture.
So first, we're going to go
through neurons, their biology,
and then how we represent
them in computational models.
Same for neural masses,
what assumptions we
make when we create
neural masses.
And then we'll
talk about sources.
And for sources, we
have plenty of options.
In Neuroblox, we have
some simple sources--
for instance, sinusoid
waves that you
can input to any blocks
or some spike trains,
like Poisson series.
But for now, I'd like to focus
on the deep brain stimulation,
because that's one
category of sources that
is very much a real
world application,
and we include this
already in Neuroblox.
So, moving on to neurons
first, as you might know,
our brain is full of them.
Human brains can have
around 10 to the 10 neurons.
There's partially
connected with each other,
but still, dendrites of
most of these neurons
receive now on average an input
from 10 to the 5 other neurons.
And also, neurons have a
soma and an axon coming out
of the soma.
The axon is how they
communicate the action potential
to the dendrites
of other neurons.
And here on the right, you
can see two images of neurons.
On the far right, we have
some pyramidal neuron
that has been actually
GFP-labeled You
can see in green.
And on the left, you
can see a drawing
that Ramon Cajal did of
Purkinje cells and granule cells
in the cerebral cortex.
So now, action potentials
are how neurons
communicate with each other.
These are chemical
signals that neurons
turn into electrical ones.
And the way that
this is done is there
is some influx of
ions from outside
on the synaptic cleft
to the inside, which
is the sum of the neuron.
Eventually, the
sum of the neuron
starts from the dendrites.
And this influx happens
through receptors,
the gates that essentially
open at different times.
And the first
computational model
that actually described
these dynamics,
these receptor
dynamics in detail,
was the famous
Hodgkin-Huxley model.
And we'll see different
flavors of this model
implement it in Neuroblox.
And another success
of this model
is essentially
because of the way
that [INAUDIBLE] were
laid out, yes, it did
describe the receptor dynamics.
But it also offered
us something else,
which is an equivalent
electrical circuit.
So this is another way of
thinking about the operation
of single neurons, right?
So we can create an
electrical circuit
with actual
electrical components
like receptors and capacitors
and battery sources.
And a circuit like this
would behave in equivalence
to an actual neuron.
So this is a nice--
both abstract but also more
practical at the same time
representation of this
computational model.
So in more detail, the plasty--
synaptic-- sorry--
transmission, as I said,
this is a chemical signal.
We have synaptic
vesicles being packaged
on the presynaptic
side, and then
they get emitted in
the synaptic cleft,
and they are picked
up by receptors
on the postsynaptic neuron,
which, consequently,
the receptors actually
open the ion channels,
and we have the ion influx
that actually causes
the postsynaptic potential
because the influx actually
potentiates the neuron.
And people have
observed these two types
of neurons we call
integrators in class I
and resonators, class II.
So we can distinguish them
by their fi-curve, which
is the firing-rate frequency
over the injected current
to the neuron.
So we have neurons
that actually,
as you inject more
and more current,
the firing rate goes up
almost proportionally
to the injected current.
But also, we have
the resonators,
which, you can think of--
they function almost
like a switch.
So up to some specific input
current level, nothing happens.
There's no firing.
And then there is a
jump to some firing
rate, which might grow
proportionally afterwards
for higher values.
And here on the
right, I just wanted
to show you essentially
some face portraits
of how this is possible.
And this is coming from
a book by Izhikevich.
This is the same
Izhikevich whose model you
have implemented, and
actually, that model
can exhibit these bifurcations.
And by bifurcation,
essentially, we
mean different configurations
of the variables
and different evolutions of
the combination of variables
that allow for either
spiking or silence or moving
between rhythmic spiking to
silence or the other way around
or moving between bursts
to single spike and so on.
And of course, to draw
diagrams like this
is much easier for simple neuron
models like the Izhikevich
neuron, which is
only two dimensional.
We can actually do this.
It's computationally
much easier compared
to doing this for a
[INAUDIBLE] neuron, which
will have more equations.
So you need to actually
explore a larger parameter set
and do this in a
simulation-based manner.
So this is also a comment
towards the benefits
of simple neuronal models.
You have a simple model.
Maybe the parameters
and the variables
that it carries like
the Izhikevich neuron,
they are less
biologically relevant.
But you know more
about the behavior
that model can exhibit more
easily, sometimes even in paper.
Right, moving on to
the second category,
these are the
neural mass models.
So you can think of neural
mass models as a step
up on the abstraction ladder.
Such models were
designed to capture,
on average, the activity
of neurons or neurons
connected to one another.
And in general, they are
oscillators or collections
of oscillators.
And here, you can see an
example of that, which
is the [INAUDIBLE] oscillator.
So these are very much
phenomenological models,
as in they don't
rely on biology.
They just imitate
this periodicity
in spiking, right, but
in very simple terms.
So they just assume
this sinusoid spiking,
and you have a pool of them.
But the handy thing about
the [INAUDIBLE] oscillators,
as you can see in
the diagram, is
that given a pool
of oscillators,
you can, by changing this
one variable in the model,
you can move from regimes of all
of the oscillators oscillating
in a similar frequency so
now you have synchronicity
to regimes where oscillators
are more uniformly scattered,
and there is no
synchronicity, or they're
split into different clusters.
So you have some
flexibility in this model.
Now, there are even more
detailed neural mass models
that allow for more
flexibility, and again, these
are all examples that we have
already included in Neuroblox,
like the Wilson-Coawn model,
which is a model that describes
an EI balance in a
neuron population,
the Jensen rate
model that is, again,
a model that
describes interactions
between pyramidal
neurons and interneurons,
or [INAUDIBLE], which
you can actually
see a face portrait of
that here on the right.
And I'm showing you
the face portrait
so you can see actually the
flexibility in this model.
So each color here
is a different regime
that the model can be in
depending on its parameter
values.
So you can actually
tune it and observe
different behaviors in this
model according to your data
as well.
So there's even more flexibility
to the simple [INAUDIBLE]
oscillators from before.
And for maximum
flexibility, I would say,
we have this next generation
neural mass models, again
already implemented
in Neuroblox.
So these models are maximally
flexible because they
are analytically-derived from a
population of neuronal models.
So we first assume how
our neurons are behaving.
For instance, there have been
already analytically-derived
in the literature
for QIF neurons.
That's the Quadratic
Integrated Firing
neurons you have seen
in previous exercises
or Izhikevich neurons that
you have implemented yourself.
So if you assume a
population of such neurons
and some connectivity
between them,
you can analytically derive
a next generation neural mass
model that is more flexible
than the previous models
that I've shown you.
And you can see an example
of this flexibility here.
For instance, this period
of synchronous activity,
synchronous spiking
in our population,
is actually longer than
the quiescence period
and the other activity periods.
So you can even
tell from this image
that this model can do more than
simple periodic activity, right?
It doesn't assume sinusoid
neurons inside it.
It's more flexible.
So it can capture
even transient periods
like that or shorter
or longer periods
of activity and quiescence.
So the final section that
I wanted to talk about
is our sources and specifically
deep brain stimulation.
So deep brain stimulation is
a neurosurgical procedure.
It has been applied--
I think one classic
application of it
is Parkinson's disease to reduce
motor symptoms like tremor
and rigidity.
The benefits of it is that it
is adjustable and reversible.
And also, it allows thus for
better medication management.
But also, now it
has been extended,
and other brain disorders
can also be treated with DBS.
So as I was saying, this is very
much a real world application,
and we're trying to match
exactly those real world
protocols in Neuroblox.
So these are two
examples of stimuli
from the DBS suite of
stimuli that we have.
For instance, you can use
this DBS simple structure
given all these parameters
with the relevant units which
will essentially create a
source that operates like this.
You have square
pulses interspersed
in some periodic manner.
And here, you can
see just a zoomed
in image of a squared pulse.
And you can have it with
smoothed corners or completely
square.
But also, we offer
more flexibility.
So you can have these more
complex protocols where
you have a burst of pulses
and then a period of silence
and then a burst again.
So this is the protocol DBS
over the previous structure
that was just DBS.
And finally, I just want to
mention that we implemented
those structures, both of
DBS, and we replicated results
from deep brain
stimulation paper
that essentially modeling
DBS in basal ganglia.
And we have a model of
this, and these are just
power spectrum results
from simulating
the model in these three regimes
under different stimulation
conditions.
And you can see more about
this in the exercises as well.
So this was my last slide.
So, similar to
previous days, you
can navigate to the
neural-- neuron masses
and source [INAUDIBLE].
This is the webpage
for the session,
and you can work on the
neural mass notebook.
So yeah, and feel free to ask
any questions at any time.
Thank you.